Finding Aid to the Richard F. Bach Records, 1913-1953 Archives.Bach.1
The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives
Richard F. Bach Records
Bulk, 1939-1953
1913-1953
Archives.Bach.1
The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives
2.5 Linear feet (6 boxes)
During his tenure at The Metropolitan Museum of Art, Richard F. Bach served as Associate in Industrial Arts (1918-1929), Director of Industrial Relations (1929-1941), Dean of Education and Extension (1941-1949), and Consultant in Industrial Arts (1949-1952). Bach championed the collaboration of museums and the industrial arts, working extensively with manufacturers, industrial designers, and educational institutions. In addition to his work at the Museum, Bach was a member and leader of a number of arts and education organizations as well as a prolific writer and lecturer. The Richard F. Bach Records primarily contain correspondence, meeting minutes, and pamphlets related to Bach’s activities as Director of Industrial Relations, Dean of Education and Extension, and Consultant in Industrial Arts. The majority of the correspondence is professional in nature and concerns Bach’s role as liaison between The Metropolitan Museum of Art and industrial designers, manufacturers, educators, and arts organizations.
Bach, Richard F., 1888-1968
Related Archival Materials note
Richard F. Bach Correspondence Files, Office of the Secretary Records, The Metropolitan Museum of Art Archives.
Scope and Contents note
The Richard F. Bach Records primarily contain correspondence, meeting minutes, and pamphlets related to Bach’s activities as Director of Industrial Relations, Dean of Education and Extension, and Consultant in Industrial Arts. The material spans the period of 1913-1953, but the bulk dates from 1939-1953 when Bach served as Dean and Consultant. Additional items in the collection include printed material, newspaper articles, radio broadcast transcripts, and photographs. The majority of the correspondence concerns Bach’s role as liaison between The Metropolitan Museum of Art and industrial designers, manufacturers, educators, and arts organizations. There is a significant amount of material related to Bach’s involvement in rehabilitation and occupational therapy, the National Council on Design Protection, the American Federation of Arts, the Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, and various exhibitions concerning American industrial art. While there is some correspondence related to personal matters, most of the material is professional in nature. Included in the collection is correspondence between Bach and various Metropolitan Museum of Art secretaries, directors, and presidents, including Henry W. Kent, Francis Henry Taylor, Herbert E. Winlock, William M. Ivins, and William Church Osborn.
Arrangement note
The Richard F. Bach Records consist of a single series arranged alphabetically by corporate name, personal name or subject.
Biographical/Historical note
During his tenure at The Metropolitan Museum of Art, Richard F. Bach served as Associate in Industrial Arts (1918-1929), Director of Industrial Relations (1929-1941), Dean of Education and Extension (1941-1949), and Consultant in Industrial Arts (1949-1952). Bach championed the collaboration of museums and the industrial arts, working extensively with manufacturers, industrial designers, and educational institutions across the United States. In addition to his work at the Museum, Bach was a member and leader of a number of arts and education organizations including the American Federation of Arts, the Architectural League of New York, and the Advisory Board on Vocational Education of the New York Board of Education. Bach was also a prolific writer and lecturer. He published several articles concerning American industrial art and a book entitled Museums and the Industrial World(1926).
Richard F. Bach was born in 1888. He graduated from Columbia University in 1908 and during 1909-1919 was an instructor and curator at Columbia’s School of Architecture. In 1918, Bach was appointed Associate in Industrial Arts at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. In this position, Bach's main role was to facilitate use of the Museum’s collections as practical resources by manufacturers, designers, artisans, and craftsmen. Bach was also primarily responsible for organizing a series of popular exhibitions devoted to American industrial art.
In 1929, Bach became the Director of Industrial Relations, heading a department created by the Museum’s Secretary, Henry W. Kent. Bach maintained the Museum’s relationships with a variety of arts, education, and industrial manufacturers’ organizations, and also supervised the Museum’s Neighborhood Exhibitions, a series of thematic shows of Museum objects that traveled to various parts of New York City during 1933-1941. In 1941, the Department of Industrial Relations merged with the Department of Educational Work, creating the Department of Education and Extension. Bach became Dean of the newly created department, managing educational loans, extension museums, industrial art exhibitions, and contacts with industrial designers and manufacturers. After World War II, Bach tried unsuccessfully to provide services at the Museum for veterans, attempting to coordinate the efforts of rehabilitation and occupational therapists with the Museum's Education Department. Bach also fostered a working relationship with the United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization during this period.
Bach resigned as Dean of Education and Extension in 1949, but continued his relationship with the Museum through 1952 as Consultant in Industrial Arts. During the later 1950s the Museum dramatically curtailed its work in the field of industrial relations. Bach continued to serve as an educational adviser to the American Institute of Interior Decorators between 1952 and 1961. Bach died in his home in the Bronx in 1968. He was survived by his widow, Maude Bransford Bach, and his two daughters, Winifred and Eleanor.
Conditions Governing Access note
Collection is open for research.
Bibliography
Howe, Winifred.A History of the Metropolitan Museum of Art: 1905-1941. New York: Columbia University Press, 1946.
New York Times. 1968. "Richard F. Bach Arts Adviser, 80," February 18.
American Federation of Arts.; Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art.; Ivins, William Mills, 1881-1961; Kent, Henry Watson, 1866-1948; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.). American Wing.; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.).; Taylor, Francis Henry, 1903-1957; Winlock, Herbert E., 1884-1950; Correspondence; Industrial arts--United States; Industrial design--20th century; Industrial design--Exhibitions; Industrial design--United States--History--20th century; Museums -- Educational aspects -- United States
- Akron Art Institute., 1945-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  See Also:
  Box 2, Folder 8 - Clear, Charles "Val". 1950-1952
- Alb-Art., 1941-1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- American Ceramic Society Inc., 1949-1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- American Council of Style and Design Inc., 1940, 1946-1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- American Federation of Arts. Art reference books., 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- American Federation of Arts. Correspondence and misc. related material., 1924, 1940-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- American Federation of Arts. Correspondence and misc. related material., 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Box 2, Folder 5 - Carnegie Corporation Grant. 1943
- American Federation of Arts - Minutes., 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- American Federation of Arts. Traveling exhibitions., 1949-1952 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- American Federation of Arts. Traveling lectures., 1938-1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- American Furniture and Industrial Art. Misc. photographs., [1925-1927], [1953] (Box 1, Folder 11)
- American Furniture and Industrial Art. Misc. photographs., [1925-1927], [1953] (Box 1, Folder 12)
- American Furniture and Industrial Art. Misc. photographs., [1925-1927], [1953] (Box 1, Folder 13)
- American Institute of Architects., 1943, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- American Institute of Steel Construction Inc., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- American Library Association., 1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- American Museum of Natural History., 1939, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Architectural League of New York., 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Architectural Record., 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Art Alliance of America., 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  General Note:
  Contains correspondence and reports related to Art Center, Inc.
- Art Commission Associates., 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Association of Arts and Industries., 1929, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Baltimore Department of Education., 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Baltimore Museum of Art., 1943 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Bel-But., 1935-1940, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Breck, Joseph., 1923-1931 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- British Council., 1940-1942 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Brooklyn Botanic Garden., 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Cal-Cra., 1933-1952 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Callisen, Sterling A., 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Carl Schurz Memorial Foundation Inc., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Carnegie Corporation Grant., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Box 1, Folder 7 - American Federation of Arts. Correspondence and misc. related material. 1951-1953.
- "Century of Progress International Exposition Chicago 1933.", 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Chicago Museum of Science and Industry., 1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Clear, Charles "Val"., 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Box 1, Folder 1 - Akron Art Institute. 1945-1953; Box 2, Folder 27 - Fab-Ful. 1941-1953
- Commerce and Industry Association of New York Inc., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Committee for a New York State Art Program., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Contemporary American Industrial Art: 1940. Exhibition correspondence., 1939-1942 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Contemporary American Industrial Art: 1940. Form letters., 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Contemporary American Industrial Art: 1940. General records., 1939-1942 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Contemporary American Industrial Art: 1940. Participating designers, craftsmen, and manufacturers. (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Contemporary American Industrial Art: 1940. Printed matter., 1937-1940 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art., 1947-1953 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Box 2, Folder 38 - Halloran General Hospital of the U.S. Army. 1943
- Creese, Walter., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Box 3, Folder 18 - J.B. Speed Museum. 1951
- Daniels, Stuart J., 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Dec-Dra., 1949-1952 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- DeSager, W. A., 1944 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Box 3, Folder 25 - Lees-McRae College. 1941-1942
- Deutscher Werkbund., 1952 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Box 3, Folder 6 - Industrial Designers' Institute. 1953
- Dowling, Henry G., 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Easby, Dudley T., Jr., 1945-1953 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Easby/Loughry Report., 1946-1952 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Eck-Edw., 1945-1947 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Edinger, Dora., 1951-1952 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Fab-Ful., 1941-1953 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  See Also
- Falkner, Etta., 1952 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Faulkner, Ray., 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Federated Council on Art Education., 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Frank, Lawrence K., 1947 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Frary, I. T., 1952 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Gar-Gug., [1913], 1947-1953 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- General Education Board., [1937] (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Grumbacher Co., 1947 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Gullberg, Elsa., 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Halloran General Hospital of the U.S. Army., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  Box 5, Folder 3 - Rehabilitation and Occupational Therapy. Correspondence and r Contemporary American Industrial Art: 1940. Exhibition correspondence.elated material. 1942-1944, 1952; Box 2, Folder 16 - Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art. 1947-1953
- Har-Hom., 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Hercules Powder Company., 1952-1953 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Higgins, John W., 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Huntington Museum., 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Ind-Int., 1926-1928, 1940-1945, 1951-1953 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Industrial Designers' Institute., 1953 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Box 2, Folder 21 - Deutscher Werkbund. 1952
- Inter-American relations. Correspondence related to inter-American relations., 1940-1945 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Inter-Society Color Council., 1951-1952 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- International Council of Museums., 1946-1952 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- International Council of Religious Education., 1943 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- International Exhibition of Modern Decorative and Industrial Arts, Paris., 1924-1925 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- International Federation for Art Education., 1928, 1937, 1949-1952 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- International Federation of Business and Professional Women., 1936-1937 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- International Textile Exhibition., 1947 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Institute of Contemporary Art., 1952 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Ivins, William M., 1934-1940 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Jar-Jut., 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- J. B. Speed Museum., 1951 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Box 2, Folder 17 - Creese, Walter. 1946
- Joel, David., 1951 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Kea-Kno., 1946, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Kent, Henry W., 1921-1928 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- La France Industries., 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Laymen's Art League of America., 1939 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Lea-Luk., 1941-1947 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Lees-McRae College., 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  Box 2, Folder 20 - DeSager, W.A. 1944
- Leland, Ernest Stevens., 1946-1947, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Lenygon, Francis. Collection., 1943-1945 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- Levy, Florence., 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Mac-Mus., 1937-1952 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- Mahogany Association Inc., 1951-1953 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Martin, Keith., [1933], 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Metropolitan Museum of Art. The Costume Institute., 1945-1950 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Metropolitan Museum of Art. Department of Industrial Relations., [1937]-1941 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Metropolitan Museum of Art. Department of Prints., 1942 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Metropolitan Museum of Art. Employees' Association., 1944-[1948?] (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Metropolitan Museum of Art. Postwar building plans., 1927-1944 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Metropolitan Museum of Art. Retirement plan., 1941-1946 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Modern Lamps and Accessories., 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Mosseller, Lillian Mills., 1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Municipal Art Society., 1939, 1945-1952 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Museum Council of New York., 1938-1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Box 5, Folder 3 - Rehabilitation and Occupational Therapy. Correspondence and related material. 1942-1944, 1952
- Museum Relations to Industry. Study by Bach., 1952-1952 (Box 4, Folder 7-10)
- Museum of Science and Industry. Newspaper clippings., 1925-1926 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Nat-New., 1945-1953 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- National Association of Manufacturers., [1950] (Box 4, Folder 13)
- National Conference of Christians and Jews Inc., 1952 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- National Council on Design Protection of the American Arbitration Asssociation. Correspondence and misc. related materials., 1931-1935, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  Box 5, Folder 5 - Robert W. Irwin Company. 1936-1938
- National Council on Design Protection of the American Arbitration Association. U.S. National Industrial Recovery Act Codes., 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- National Education-Recreation Council., 1943-1950 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- National Society of Mural Painters Inc., 1936 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- New York Adult Education Council., 1943-1949 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- New York (N.Y.) Board of Education. Advisory Board on Vocational Education., 1944-1952 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- New York Phoenix School of Design., 1945-1950 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- New York World's Fair., 1938-1940 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- O'Co-Off., 1945-1949 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- O'Meara, Dennis., 1944 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Osborn, William Church., 1943-1952 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Paris International Exposition., 1937 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Patrick Dolan and Associates Inc., 1950 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Paul MacAlister and Associate., 1951 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Perry, Henrietta., 1947-1948 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Progressive Education Association., 1933 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Rai-Rod., 1934, 1941-1953 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Rehabilitation and Occupational Therapy. Correspondence and related material., 1942-1944, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  Box 2, Folder 38 - Halloran General Hospital of the U.S. Army. 1943; Box 4, Folder 6 - Museum Council of New York City. 1938-1953
- Related Arts Service., 1944-1947 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Robert W. Irwin Company., 1936-1938 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  Contains correspondence related to the Grand Rapids Furniture Museum
  Box 4, Folder 11 - National Council on Design Protection of the American Arbitration Asssociation. Correspondence and misc. related materials. 1931-1935, 1948
- Rogers, Cleveland., 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Sam-Str., 1938-1953 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Sanborn, Herbert., 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Saxe, John Godfrey., 1942 (Box 5, Folder 23)
- School Art League., 1945-1953 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Shipway, Verna., 1951-1953 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Society of Industrial Designers., 1950-1953 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Society for the Preservation of New England Antiquities., 1940, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  Contains correspondence with the Bucks County Historical Society
- Stavenow, Ake., 1953 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Stout, George.Conservation of Paintings., 1943 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Sutherland, Beth Benton., 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Svenska, Slojdforeningen., 1936-1938, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Syracuse Museum of Fine Arts., 1935-1936, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Tat-Tra., 1940, 1950-1952 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Taggart, Edwin L.M., 1948-1951, 1953 (Box 5, Folder 34)
- Taylor, Francis Henry., 1940-1953 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Tennessee Valley Authority., 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  contains correspondence and misc. related material concerning the United States Department of Labor, Women's Bureau
- Thomas, Steven., 1952 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Toledo Museum of Art., 1946-1952 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Transcripts of radio announcements and related material., 1934-1936 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- University of C-University of M., 1946-1953 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization (UNESCO)., 1947-1953 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- United States. Department of Commerece., 1931-1936 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- United States. Department of State., 1938-1944 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- United States. Executive Office of the President- Dwight D. Eisenhower., 1945 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- United States. Federal Public Housing Authority., 1942 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- United States. Misc. government departments., 1945-1951 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- United States. Office of War Information., 1942 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- United States. Resettlement Administration., 1936 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- United States. Veterans Administration., 1946-1952 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- United States. Works Progress Administration., 1938-1942, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 16)
- University of the State of New York., 1948 (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Virginia Murphy Memorial Scholarship., 1950 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Wadsworth Atheneum., 1947-1950 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Wal-Woo., 1931, 1943-1953 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Wallpaper Museum. Correspondence related to a planned museum., 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Winebrenner, Kenneth D., 1950 (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Winlock, Herbert E., 1932-1938 (Box 6, Folder 23)